Finding Aid for Elizabeth W. Bauer papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth W. Bauer papers
1958-2013
1970s-2000s
Bauer, Elizabeth W.
2014055 Aa 2
Elizabeth W. Bauer is a disability rights activist who served many years defending the rights of the disabled within Michigan, across the country, and internationally. She also served an eight year term on Michigan's State Board of Education. This collection contains materials relating to different disability rights issues--such as deinstitutionalization, community placement, euthanasia, sterilization, and disability legislation--as well as papers regarding the many organizations through which Bauer enacted her work.
17 linear feet
78.3 MB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Elizabeth W. Bauer (donor number 10,999 ) in September 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Elizabeth W. Bauer, born December 28, 1937, received her Bachelor of Arts in Religion with a Minor in Speech Pathology from Mount Holyoke College in South Hadley, Mass. Upon her graduation, Bauer conducted post graduate study in Speech Pathology at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis. Bauer then continued her education at The Ohio State University in Columbus, where she received her Master of Arts in Education for Exceptional Children. She completed her studies by conducting doctoral studies at Michigan State University in East Lansing, in Education Administration.
After moving to Michigan in 1975, Bauer began her career in public service as an Adult Special Education Services Administrator and Special Education Teaching Consultant within the School District of the City of Pontiac in Pontiac. During this time, Bauer was responsible for identifying and creating education placements for people with disabilities over the age of 18. Within this position, she helped more than 200 people complete educational programs (Adult Basic Education, GED, High School Diploma) and become gainfully employed.
Bauer then went on to serve as Director of training for the Michigan Department of Mental Health at its Plymouth Center for Human Development in Northville, Mich. In this position, she was responsible for directing 30 professional and paraprofessional educators to provide staff development programs for more than 1,000 facility personnel. At the time, the Plymouth Center for Human Development was under court order to upgrade its services. Bauer directed that staff receive 120 hours of pre-service and 80 hours of in-service training, and built a training program that became the model of public mental health facilities in Michigan.
Next, Bauer worked as an administrator within the Developmental Disabilities Community Residential Services Division of the Michigan Department of Mental Health. In this position, Bauer directed a staff to coordinate the task of four Michigan Mental Health agencies to develop community-based residential services for persons with developmental disabilities in Wayne, Oakland, and Macomb counties. This effort resulted in helping more than 1,000 persons with mental and developmental disabilities to leave institutional settings for real homes in the community, in addition to school programs and community jobs.
In 1981, Elizabeth Bauer founded and became the executive director of Michigan Protection and Advocacy Service (MPAS)--Michigan's federally mandated protection and advocacy system for people with disabilities. The organization was designated to implement protection and advocacy systems for people with developmental disabilities, mental illness, HIV/AIDS and other disabilities pursuant to federal and state laws. During her time as executive director, MPAS was able to help thousands of people with disabilities achieve their objectives of protection from abuse, neglect, and discrimination and trained thousands to advocate for themselves and others.
After retiring from MPAS in 2001, Bauer was elected in 2002 to the State Board of Education for an eight year term during which time she led the State Board's educational technology initiative and was a member of the National Association of State Boards of Education (NASBE) Work Group on Career and Technical Education. She received the NASBE Distinguished Service Award in 2012.
In addition to her work with MPAS and the Michigan School Board of Education, beginning in 1994, Bauer worked as a self-employed consultant, focusing on human rights, civil society, and organization development with particular attention to rights and opportunities for people with disabilities in the United States, as well as countries including Armenia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Georgia, Hungary, Kosovo, Mexico, Peru, Romania, Russia, Serbia, Turkey, Ukraine, and Vietnam. As of 2014, in addition to her continuing work as a consultant, Bauer serves as president of the Board of Directors for the Widening Advancements for Youth (WAY) Academy of Detroit, a Charter school for students in need in South West Detroit, Mich.
Collection contains materials relating to different disability rights issues, records regarding the many organizations through which Bauer enacted her work, papers relating to Bauer's term as an elected official on the State Board of Education, materials relating to the conferences and workshops Bauer held and attended, Bauer's speeches and writings, and a very small personal series.
The collection is divided into seven series: the Personal series, the Organizations series, the Social Issues series (divided into 7 subseries: Bio-ethics and Disability Rights, Building Feasibility Study, Community Living/Group Homes, Deinstitutionalization, Mental Disability and the Law, Patient Abuse, and Miscellaneous), the Education series, the Conferences and Workshops series, the International Consultation series, and the Speeches and Writings series.
Subjects:
Bauer, Elizabeth W.; Euthanasia--Michigan.; Group homes for people with disabilities--Michigan.; Michigan. State Board of Education.; Michigan Protection & Advocacy Service.; People with disabilities--Michigan.; People with disabilities--Deinstitutionalization--Michigan.; People with disabilities--Legal status, laws, etc.--Michigan.; Special education--Michigan.; Sterilization (Birth control)--Moral and ethical aspects--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series (0.1 linear feet, 1979-2011) contains a paper written by Elizabeth Bauer's daughter, Anna McTigue, family photographs, personal correspondence, and Bauer's submission to Who's Who in the Midwest in 1979.
  - Daughter Anna's paper, undated (Box 1)
  - Family photographs with, undated; 1979 (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence, 1981-2011 (Box 1)
    (with gaps)
  - Who's Who in the Midwest submission, 1979 (Box 1)
- Organizations
  The Organizations series (3.5 linear feet, 1971-2012) includes material related to different organizations Elizabeth Bauer was associated with, whose primary concerns were disability issues, services, and policy. The series consists of meeting agenda and minutes, handwritten notes taken by Bauer, correspondences, memorandums, newsletters, newspaper clippings, reports, and program information regarding programs run by these organizations that Bauer was a part of.
  - Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Oakland County
    - Evaluation and Recommendations: Mental Health Services for Seriously Mentally Ill Adults of Oakland County, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter, 1988 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees Facility Closure Agreement with the Department of Mental Health, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Association for Macomb-Oakland Regional Center
    - Annual reports, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
    - Audit report, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Background/administrative, 1977 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Monitoring committee guidelines, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 1976-1987 (Box 1)
    - Residential task force, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Site visit report, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Association for Persons with Severe Handicaps (TASH) Newsletters, 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Association for Retarded Citizens of Oakland County Profiles newsletters, 1974-1988 (Box 1)
  - Association for Retarded Citizens/Michigan
    - Background/administrative, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Family Support Minority Outreach Project, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Project to Assure Services for Handicapped Citizens, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Community Mental Health Board
    - Authority Task Force Draft Final Report and Plan, 1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Background/administrative, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - Human resources, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Performance Audit of the Oakland County Community Mental Health Services Board, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Council for Exceptional Children Government Report Insight Newsletters, 1973-1980; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Council for Retarded Citizens, Inc.
    - Background/administrative, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - Planning committee, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Respite care, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Staff advocacy reports, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Volunteer visitation, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Department of Mental Health (Box 2)
    - AFSCME lawsuit, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Audit Report: Treatment Outcome for Developmentally Disabled Clients of the Specialized Residential Services Program, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
    - Background/administrative, 1980-1991 (Box 2)
      (scattered)
    - DMH vision and responses, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Department of Mental Health (cont.)
    - DMH-3800B contracts, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Final Report of the Quality Care Task Force, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Medicaid Mental Health Clinic Services Program, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Mental health booklets, 1980-1990 (Box 2)
    - Mental Health Coalition Sub-committee on Facility Utilization, Employee Issues, etc., 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Department of Mental Health LINK, 1971-1979 (Box 2)
    - Principles for Services to Individuals with Disabilities and their Families, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Report on Medical Malpractice Insurance, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Residential Monitoring Pilot for DMH Contract Homes, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Franklin County Council for Retarded Citizens, Inc., 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Governor's Task Force on Access to Health Care, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Region Mental Health Newsletter, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Alliance for Psychiatric Alternatives, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Home Alliance, 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Michigan League for Human Services, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Protection and Advocacy Service
    - ADD Program's Roadmap to the Future, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Background/administrative, 1986-2012 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence re. Bauer's retirement from MPAS, 2001 (Box 2)
    - The disability vote with gaps, 1983-2012; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Exchange newsletter, 1983-2001 (Box 2)
    - Executive director search, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Freedom of Information Act request, 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Goal One: Quality Community Services, 1992 (Box 2)
    - A Manual for Building Advocacy Skills, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Monitoring logs for Plymouth Center for Human Development, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Monitoring protocols, 1983; 1990 (Box 2)
    - MPAS general correspondence, 1983-2013 (Box 3)
    - NAPAS Annual Report on State Program Activities, 1989 (Box 3)
    - NAPAS Olmstead Progress Reports, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - North Carolina Department of Administration Governor's Advocacy Council for Persons with Disabilities Consultation, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Principles for human services, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Program Administration Review of the Michigan Protection and Advocacy Service for Developmentally Delayed Citizens, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Protective Services/Recipient Rights Report, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Reaction to Voice of the Retarded in Exceptional Parent, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Reauthorization of the Rehabilitation Act of, 1973; 1986 (Box 3)
    - Repeal special education law, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Report to Governor Blanchard's transition team, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Report to Governor Engler's transition team, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Service plan, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - State-run group homes, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Statewide Independent Living Council, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - National Association of Vocational Education Special Needs Personnel, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - National Home of Your Own Alliance, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - New Directions: National Association of State Mental Retardation Program Directors, Inc., 1978 (Box 3)
  - New Horizons of Oakland County Incorporated, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - Northern Virginia Association for Retarded Children, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Oakdale Regional Center for Developmental Disabilities, 1975-1978 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Regional Interagency, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Ohio Association for Retarded Citizens, Inc.
    - Background/administrative, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - Legal and Government Affairs Committee, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Ohio Developmental Disabilities, Inc., 1974 (Box 3)
  - Ohio Horizons Committee Survey Project, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Parents Organization of Special Education, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania Association for Retarded Children, Inc., 1973 (Box 3)
  - Plymouth Center for Human Development
    - Communicator newsletters, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Consent Decree Implementation Unit Compliance Audits, 1980 (Box 3)
    - General correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Liz Bauer interviews with PCHD, undated (Box 3)
    - MARC et al. vs. Donald Smith et al., 1981-1989 (Box 3)
    - Meeting with monitors report, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978-1984 (Box 3)
    - PCHD deposition materials, 1980-1982; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - PCHD staff attrition plan, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Personal Assessment of the Developmental Stages of PCHD Training Department (July-December 1978), 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Perspectives newsletter, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
    - Placement referrals by responsible agency, undated (Box 4)
    - Plymouth Consent Decree, 1979-1989 (Box 4)
    - Quality Assurance Proposal, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Quarterly Reports-Plymouth Consent Decree, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Recreational activities information, 1974-1978 (Box 4)
  - President's Committee on Mental Retardation, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Task Force on Developmental Disabilities Service Planning, 1975 (Box 4)
  - United Cerebral Palsy Association of Metropolitan Detroit, undated (Box 4)
  - Wayne Community Living Services
    - Community placement program, undated (Box 4)
    - Newsletters, 1985-1989 (Box 4)
    - Performance Audit of the Residential Services Program, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Updated plan for transfer responsibility
      - 1989 (Box 4)
      - 1991 (Box 4)
- Social Issues
  The Social Issues series (7 linear feet, 1963-2013) contains material relating to different social issues particularly pertinent to disability rights. The series has been divided into seven subseries.
  - Bio-ethics and Disability Rights
    The Bio-ethics and Disability Rights subseries (1.3 linear feet, 1972-2013) details issues such as assisted suicide, euthanasia, genetics procedures, refusal of medical services, rationing care to the developmentally disabled, and sterilization of the developmentally disabled. The subseries contains information on high profile court cases regarding these issues, meeting minutes and notes from the Children's Hospital of Michigan Bio-ethics Committee, newspaper clippings, newsletters, research papers, and correspondence.
    - Ashley Treatment, 2006-2010 (Box 4)
    - Assisted suicide/end of life, 1992-2000 (Box 4)
    - Baby Allison case, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Baby Doe, 1982-1988 (Box 4)
    - Children's Hospital of Michigan Bio-ethics Committee, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Children's Hospital of Michigan Bio-ethics Committee, 1984-1985; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Deciding to Forego Life-Sustaining Treatment, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Genetics newspaper clippings, 1981-2000 (Box 5)
    - Genome Technology and Reproduction: Values and Public Policy (Michigan State University), 1996-2001; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Guardian's refusal of medical services-MPAS, 1997 (Box 5)
    - House Bill 4175-Right to Refuse Treatment, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Merian's Friends, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Medical ethics Resource Network of Michigan, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Michael Martin court case, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Probate and estate Planning Journal, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Task Force for Child Abuse Amendments of, 1984 (Box 5)
    - MPAS' death and dying procedure proposal, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings re. denying care, 1983-2009 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings re. euthanasia/assisted suicide, 1985-2001 (with gaps); 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Not Dead Yet, 1996-2001 (Box 5)
    - Pre-natal testing and disability, 1982-2007 (Box 5)
    - Public Health Committee Public Hearings, 1981; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Rationing care to developmentally disabled, 1989-1994 (Box 5)
    - Sterilization correspondence, 1972-2011 (Box 5)
    - Sterilization of the developmentally disabled in Michigan, 1972-1994 (Box 6)
    - Sterilization newspaper articles, 1977-2013 (Box 6)
    - Wirsing sterilization case appeal, 1986-1998 (Box 6)
  - Building Feasibility Study
    The Building Feasibility Study subseries (0.3 linear feet, 1990-1990) concerns a study conducted by the Michigan Department of Mental Health in order to analyze facility needs to support state mental health services. This subseries contains correspondence regarding the study, the executive summary and background information of the study, as well as the many reports conducted in relation to the study.
    - Correspondence re. study, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Demand and Catchment Area Analysis, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Executive summary, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Inventory Survey and evaluation of Existing Facilities, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Prototype Psychiatric Hospital Generic Program Statement, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Community Living/Group Homes
    The Community Living/Group Homes subseries (3.4 linear feet, 1975-2003) details issues involved with helping those who are developmentally disabled assimilate into community settings and the push-back from communities against group homes. This subseries includes litigation involving group home cases, research papers, newspaper clippings, notes taken by Bauer, correspondence, testimonies by Bauer regarding the issue, surveys and reports, and informational booklets and resource guides.
    - AAMD council, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - ARC of Michigan Community Placement Think Tank, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Bay County community opposition to group homes, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Booklets re. group homes, 1982-1986 (Box 6)
    - C.K. Homes litigation, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Cleburne Living Center, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Community and Family Living Amendments of 1983 (Bauer Testimony), 1983 (Box 6)
    - Community living arrangements for DD children with continuing nursing needs, 1987 (Box 6)
    - Community living quotes, 1979-1984 (Box 6)
    - Community residential services, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Corporation for Supportive Housing, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence re. nursing homes, 1982-2000 (Box 6)
    - Court cases re. community placement, 1976-1991; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Dental care issues, 1988 (Box 6)
    - The Detroit News adult foster care series, 1993 (Box 6)
    - DMH fact sheets re. group homes, 1982-1985 (Box 6)
    - Establishment and Development of Residential Care Facilities for Developmentally Disabled Citizens in Michigan: A Survey of Michigan Law, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Housing resources, 1993-1996 (Box 6)
    - Interim Report on Community Placement of Mentally Disabled Persons in Michigan, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Issues in adult foster care homes with, 1981-1982; 1993 (Box 7)
    - Kope experts, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Liz Bauer's notes re. community living with, undated; 1985 (Box 7)
    - Michigan laws re. group homes, 1977-1986 (Box 7)
    - Monitoring residential settings with, undated; 1980 (Box 7)
    - New Neighbors: The Retarded Citizen in Quest of a Home, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1977-2003; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Notes re. challenges to group homes, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Nursing home litigation (Kope, et al. v. Watkins, et al.), 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Nursing home litigation (Kope, et al. v. Watkins, et al.), 1988-1989; 8 folders (Box 8)
    - Oshtemo Nursing Home, 1982-1984 (Box 8)
    - Papers re. community placement in Michigan, 1978-1988 (Box 8)
    - Report on the run for community living, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Resource Guide on Community Placement for Persons with Mental Retardation, 1982 (Box 8)
    - Response to Senator Emmons re. community living, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Response to Sylvia Porter's columns on group homes, 1983 (Box 8)
    - S. 2053 Community and Family Living Amendments Act, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
    - Senate Bill no. 179-Legislation Restricting Community Placement Opportunities for Mentally Retarded Persons, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Senate Bill no. 301-Adult Foster Care Facility Licensing Act, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Southgate ordinance-adult foster care homes, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Special education programs for residents of regional centers for the developmentally delayed, 1978-1984 (Box 8)
    - Strategies of Home Placement Siting and Acceptance: A Descriptive Pilot Study of High and Low Resistance Settings in the Detroit Metropolitan Area, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Summary and Analysis of Legal Challenges to the Community Placement Process in Michigan, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Task Force on Community Placement, 1981-1984 (Box 8)
    - Testimonies re. S. 2053, 1984-1986 (Box 9)
    - Warren Village, 1982-1986 (Box 9)
    - Watervliet Home-resolution against group home, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Zoning and community placement, 1975-1977 (Box 9)
  - Deinstitutionalization
    The Deinstitutionalization subseries (1 linear foot, 1973-2012) details the issue of the closure of state mental health institutions, particularly those associated with the state of Michigan. This subseries contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, reports, public hearings, and photographs, as well as information regarding the shut-downs of specific state institutions and the transfer of patients.
    - An Economic Perspective on Deinstitutionalization, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Arnell Engstrom Children's Center, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Brook Run (Bauer consultation), 1995-1997 (Box 9)
    - Clinton Valley Center, 1982-2000 (Box 9)
    - Coldwater Regional Mental Health Center, 1991-1992 (Box 9)
    - Columbus State Institute, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Detroit public hearing, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Facility closure lawsuit, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Hillcrest transfers, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
    - Kalamazoo Regional Psychiatric Hospital, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Lafayette Clinic, 1992-1993 (Box 9)
    - Lansing public hearing, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Marquette public hearing, 1988 (Box 9)
    - MHAS hospital public hearings, 1988 (Box 9)
    - MPAS Responses to Voice of the Retarded, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Mt. Pleasant Regional Center, 1992-2012 (Box 9)
    - Muskegon Regional Center, 1989-1992 (Box 9)
    - Newberry Regional Mental Health Center, 1982 (Box 9)
    - North Country Community Mental Health, 2010 (Box 9)
    - Northville Psychiatric Hospital, 1988-2006 (Box 9)
    - Oakdale Regional Center with, 1988-1991; 2012 (Box 9)
    - P&A public hearing transcripts, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Pennhurst Longitudinal Study
      - 1979-1994 (Box 9)
      - Pennhurst Longitudinal Study: Combined Report of Five Years of Research and Analysis, 1985 (Box 9)
      - Pennhurst Study: 3rd Year Summary, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Mental Disability and the Law
    The Mental Disability and the Law subseries (0.4 linear feet, 1969-2012) contains materials relating to the history of law relating to mental disability. Included in this subseries are reports, legislative correspondence, the Michigan Bar Journal, court cases, and disability laws.